<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<eml:eml xmlns:eml="https://eml.ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.2.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:stmml="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.2" packageId="knb-lter-nes.24.2" xsi:schemaLocation="https://eml.ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.2.0/eml.xsd https://eml.ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.2.0/eml.xsd" system="edi">
  <access authSystem="https://pasta.edirepository.org/authentication" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
    <allow>
      <principal>uid=NES,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
      <permission>all</permission>
    </allow>
    <allow>
      <principal>public</principal>
      <permission>read</permission>
    </allow>
  </access>
  <dataset>
    <title>Zooplankton sample inventory for Northeast U.S. Shelf Long Term Ecological Research (NES-LTER) Transect cruises, ongoing since 2017</title>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Sarah</givenName>
        <givenName>G</givenName>
        <surName>Glancy</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Northeast U.S. Shelf LTER</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>sglancy@whoi.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Joel</givenName>
        <givenName>K</givenName>
        <surName>Llopiz</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Northeast U.S. Shelf LTER</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>jllopiz@whoi.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </creator>
    <associatedParty>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Julia</givenName>
        <surName>Cox</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Northeast U.S. Shelf LTER</organizationName>
      <role>technician</role>
    </associatedParty>
    <pubDate>2023-03-30</pubDate>
    <abstract>
      <para>This dataset lists the inventory of physical samples from zooplankton net tows conducted on Northeast U.S. Shelf Long-Term Ecological Research (NES-LTER) Transect cruises, ongoing since 2017. The NES-LTER transect lies south of Martha’s Vineyard, Massachusetts. Dedicated NES-LTER cruises target summer and winter seasons, with samples collected in oblique tows with a bongo net fitted with 150 and 335 micron mesh nets, as well as a ring net with a 20 micron mesh net. Additional cruises along the NES-LTER Transect, including spring and fall cruises with the Ocean Observatories Initiative, collect samples in vertical tows using a ring net with 150 micron mesh net. Samples are shared with different labs for purposes including DNA metabarcoding, stable isotopes, and morphological identification.
</para>
    </abstract>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>populations</keyword>
      <keyword>organic matter</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>LTER Core Research Areas</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>zooplankton</keyword>
      <keyword>transects</keyword>
      <keyword>marine</keyword>
      <keyword>oceanography</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>LTER Controlled Vocabulary</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>Bongo net</keyword>
      <keyword>ring net</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>SeaVoX Device Catalogue</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>Single net or net pair oblique tow</keyword>
      <keyword>Single net or net pair vertical tow</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>BODC Sampling net gear deployment vocabulary</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>Northeast U.S. Continental Shelf</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>NOAA Large Marine Ecosystems</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <additionalInfo>
      <para>This data package includes data from MIT-WHOI Joint Program (JP) cruises funded by WHOI Academic Programs Office, with Chief Scientists Glen Gawarkiewicz (AR38) and Joel Llopiz (AR32 and AR63).
For other cruises on R/V Neil Armstrong, we thank the Ocean Observatories Initiative, funded by the National Science Foundation under Cooperative Agreement No. 1743430.
</para>
    </additionalInfo>
    <intellectualRights>
      <para>This data package is released to the "public domain" under Creative Commons CC0 1.0 "No Rights Reserved" (see: https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). It is considered professional etiquette to provide attribution of the original work if this data package is shared in whole or by individual components. A generic citation is provided for this data package on the website https://portal.edirepository.org (herein "website") in the summary metadata page. Communication (and collaboration) with the creators of this data package is recommended to prevent duplicate research or publication. This data package (and its components) is made available "as is" and with no warranty of accuracy or fitness for use. The creators of this data package and the website shall not be liable for any damages resulting from misinterpretation or misuse of the data package or its components. Periodic updates of this data package may be available from the website. Thank you.
</para>
    </intellectualRights>
    <coverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>NES-LTER Transect</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-70.8833</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-70.445</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>41.325</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>39.7733</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>2018-01-31</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>2021-11-11</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <maintenance>
      <description>ongoing</description>
    </maintenance>
    <contact>
      <organizationName>Northeast U.S. Shelf LTER</organizationName>
      <positionName>Nes-Lter Information Manager</positionName>
      <electronicMailAddress>lter-nes-info@whoi.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </contact>
    <methods>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <para># Field operations for net tows</para>
          <para>Here, we summarize the field operations for net tows, since the focus of this data package is on the sample preparation in the lab on board ship. Field operations for net tows are logged in the event log data package [knb-lter-nes.20] for Transect cruises, and results from sample analyses will be detailed in separate data packages, e.g., zooplankton abundance.</para>
          <para>1. Field operations for oblique tow bongo/ring net
During dedicated transect cruises (i.e. winter and summer, aboard the Endeavor), zooplankton is sampled at each regular transect station (LTER1 – LTER11). Zooplankton is collected with 61-cm diameter bongo nets, one of which has 335-µm mesh and the other 150-µm mesh (each is 3.2 m long, as they have similar porosity values—45% and 46%). A General Oceanics mechanical flowmeter is attached in the center of each mouth. In addition to the bongo nets, a 30-cm-diameter, 20-µm-mesh ring net is attached ~2 m above the bongo frame with a book clamp. This net is non-quantitative and is only used for size fraction stable isotope analysis—specifically the 20-100 µm and 100-200 µm fractions.
Tows are single oblique (down then up only once) towing at a speed through the water of 1.5 to 2.0 knots. Target net depth is 5 m off the bottom or 200 m (when bottom depth exceeds 200 m).</para>
          <para>2. Field operations for vertical tow ring net 
During transect cruises with collaborators (i.e., OOI in spring and fall), zooplankton is sampled at each regular transect station (LTER1 – LTER11). Zooplankton is collected with a 30cm ring net with 150-µm mesh (2 m long with a porosity of 46%). The tow is a single vertical tow after sending the weight to 1 m off the bottom (the mouth of the net will be 3 m off of the bottom) as determined by a CTD or onboard bottom sounder, while Armstrong uses dynamic positioning systems to remain stationary. Winch pay out and retrieval speed will be 30 m/min. </para>
          <para># Sampling protocols</para>
          <para>1. Sampling protocol for oblique tow bongo/ring net
Upon retrieval, nets are rinsed with a seawater hose to collect all plankton in the cod ends. Cod ends are carefully removed (and not until the water level is below the cod end opening) while sitting within a bucket. Labeled cod ends are then brought inside within their similarly labeled buckets (distinguishing between the 335-µm and 150-µm mesh nets) for processing in the wet lab. Samples are split with a Folsom splitter according to an established plan for where the aliquots are going for the various planned analyses—specifically, preserved in a 5% buffered formalin-seawater solution or 95% ethanol, or frozen. 
These splits and their method of preservation are: </para>
          <para>- 335 µm mesh net:</para>
          <para>- - ¾ split into 5% buffered formalin-seawater solution (for morphological IDs—to NOAA)</para>
          <para>- - ¼ split in 95% ethanol (available for DNA metabarcoding—to Rynearson lab)</para>
          <para>- 150 µm mesh net:</para>
          <para>- - ¼ split into 95% ethanol (for morphological IDs—to Llopiz lab)</para>
          <para>- - ¼ split into 95% ethanol (for DNA metabarcoding—to Rynearson lab)</para>
          <para>- - ¼ split to be size fractionated on board (&gt;1000 µm, 500-1000 µm, and 200-500 µm) for stable isotope analyses. Size fractions are frozen (-20°C) in vials.</para>
          <para>- - ¼ split for fresh sorting on board and freezing of individual taxa (or the split will be frozen for later sorting of taxa in the lab) for stable isotope analyses—4 dominant taxa of copepods (e.g. Calanus, Centropages, Pseudocalanus, Oithona), as well as appendicularians and chaetognaths.</para>
          <para>Detailed checklist of tasks and steps:
Upon retrieval</para>
          <para>- Record flowmeter readings for each net</para>
          <para>- Rinse nets from the outside of the net only, starting high and rinse all the way down to the cod end</para>
          <para>- If there are a few large organisms in the sample (e.g. jellies), remove them prior to splitting and preserve them separately in ethanol. Use the large (~5 mm) sieve if needed. Note on the event log which net they were removed from, and label their jar appropriately.</para>
          <para>- Rinse all sieves and anything with sample on it between all samples</para>
          <para>- Rinse all gear with freshwater when sampling has ended for the cruise</para>
          <para>- For 335 µm sample:</para>
          <para>- - Split sample with Folsom splitter. </para>
          <para>- - Put 3/4 of the net into a glass quart jar with formalin to a 12% formalin/seawater mix, buffer with 1:1 disodium phosphate:monosodium phosphate.</para>
          <para>- - Drain and gather the remaining ¼ split onto a ≤335-µm-mesh sieve and preserve in 95% ethanol using a glass pint jar. Jar should be at least 2/3’s full of ethanol  and 1/3 or less of plankton.</para>
          <para>- - Make sure each sample has the correct internal and external label on it.</para>
          <para>- - Store samples separately.</para>
          <para>- For the 150 µm sample:</para>
          <para>- - Split sample with Folsom splitter..</para>
          <para>- - Preserve two ¼ splits in 95% ethanol by draining and gathering each on a 150 µm mesh sieve and transferring to a plastic pint jar using a squirt bottle of ethanol (one sample goes to Llopiz lab, one to Rynearson lab)</para>
          <para>- - One of the remaining ¼ splits gets size fractionated on 1000 µm, 500 µm, and 200 µm sieves, and what is collected on each sieve gets drained and transferred to a cryovial and then frozen at -20°C</para>
          <para>- - The other ¼ split will be drained and frozen at maximum -20 celcius</para>
          <para>- - Place ethanol-preserved splits in their appropriate boxes (Llopiz and Rynearson labs)</para>
          <para>- For the 20 µm net sample:</para>
          <para>- - This sample is non-quantitative. target a well mixed sub-sample. </para>
          <para>- - Size fractions 100-200 µm and 20-100-µm are retained, drained and transferred to a cryovial and then frozen at -20°C
24 hrs after sampling</para>
          <para>- Drain and replace ethanol of ethanol-preserved samples and note the date changed on the external jar labels and on the bongo event log sheet. </para>
          <para>- Test pH of formalin sample sand add additional buffer if pH is &lt;7
Post-cruise</para>
          <para>- Ensure that samples get to respective labs and advise on which, if any, samples need additional ethanol changes.</para>
          <para>2. Sampling protocol for vertical tow ring net
Only seawater is used to collect the sample on the sieve to ready for preservation. The entire sample will go into a single jar with 95% ethanol (see notes below on removing gelatinous organisms). Ethanol will be changed 24hrs after initial preservation. </para>
          <para>- Drain the contents into a 150-µm sieve, and use pre-filtered seawater to rinse the cod end. Make sure the mesh on the cod end is rinsed well. </para>
          <para>- If there are a few large organisms in the sample (e.g. gelatinous or fish), remove them and preserve them separately in ethanol. Use the large (~5 mm) sieve if needed. </para>
          <para>- Transfer entire sample to a plastic 160z or 4oz jar depending on sample density.</para>
          <para>- Make sure each sample has the correct internal and external label.</para>
          <para>- Rinse all sieves and anything with sample on it with freshwater between all stations.</para>
          <para>- Rinse all gear with freshwater when sampling has ended for the cruise.
24 hrs after sampling</para>
          <para>- Drain and replace ethanol of ethanol-preserved samples and note the date changed on the external jar labels and on the bongo event log sheet.</para>
          <para>- Note the date changed on the external jar labels and on the ring net event log sheet. </para>
          <para># Storage protocols post-cruise</para>
          <para>Post-cruise sample allocation and storage:</para>
          <para>Llopiz lab</para>
          <para>- samples stored: </para>
          <para>- - Ethanol-MorphID</para>
          <para>- - Frozen SIA</para>
          <para>- - Frozen Taxa-picking</para>
          <para>- short term storage</para>
          <para>- - samples are examined for proper preservation and ethanol is changed if needed, date of change is recorded on the jar.</para>
          <para>- - a layer of electrical tape is wrapped around the opening of the jar to prevent evaporation</para>
          <para>- - jars are placed in cardboard boxes organized roughly by cruise and date.</para>
          <para>- - boxes are labeled with the cruise IDs and MVCO dates if applicable. </para>
          <para>- - boxes of samples are stored in Llopiz lab: Redfield 226 with ethanol safety tag on outside of box.</para>
          <para>- Long term storage</para>
          <para>- - samples are moved to BioSpecs in Llopiz storage area. </para>
          <para>- - in addition to the writing on box for short term storage, sticker labels available from Phil Alatalo at WHOI are affixed to the boxes and the accompanying data sheet online is filled out.</para>
          <para>Rynearson Lab</para>
          <para>- samples stored:</para>
          <para>- - Ethanol-150-metabarcoding</para>
          <para>- - Ethanol-335-metabarcoding</para>
          <para>- - Samples are checked a) for proper, legible labeling and b) to ensure ethanol was exchanged after the initial fixation. If needed, labels are improved and ethanol is exchanged where not yet done.</para>
          <para>- - Samples are stored in labeled cardboard boxes in drawers in the Rynearson lab.</para>
          <para>Richardson working group</para>
          <para>- - Formalin-MorphID</para>
          <para>- - in plankton lab on NEFSC Narragansett campus in Narragansett, RI</para>
          <para>- - Samples are shipped to Poland a maximum of 3 times a year.  These samples are processed following MARMAP NEFSC Sorting Protocols 5.3.1 ECOSYSTEM MONITORING - ZOOPLANKTON</para>
          <para>- - what we receive back for each sample are:</para>
          <para>- - - Ichthyoplankton:</para>
          <para>- - - 1) vial of cephalopod paralarvae (not IDed to species)</para>
          <para>- - - 2) vial of fish eggs (not IDed to species)</para>
          <para>- - - 3) one vial of larval fish for each taxa</para>
          <para>- - - Zooplankton</para>
          <para>- - - 1) Quarter aliquot of the sample</para>
          <para>- - - 2) vial of individuals for each taxa from the 400+ aliquot of individuals.  In some cases taxa are combined in the vials.</para>
          <para>- - these are archived at the Narragansett Lab where we have samples dating back to the 1970s</para>
          <para># Quality assurance and data package assembly</para>
          <para>The inventory of physical samples from zooplankton net tows is compiled in a spreadsheet with validation for manual data entry. Data package assembly with metadata templates was completed in R, with documentation available at https://github.com/WHOIGit/nes-lter-zooplankton-transect-inventory.
</para>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
    </methods>
    <project>
      <title>Northeast U.S. Shelf LTER</title>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Heidi</givenName>
          <surName>Sosik</surName>
        </individualName>
        <electronicMailAddress>hsosik@whoi.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4591-2842</userId>
        <role>Principal Investigator</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Stace</givenName>
          <surName>Beaulieu</surName>
        </individualName>
        <electronicMailAddress>sbeaulieu@whoi.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2609-5453</userId>
        <role>Co-Principal Investigator</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Changsheng</givenName>
          <surName>Chen</surName>
        </individualName>
        <electronicMailAddress>c1chen@umassd.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8715-6101</userId>
        <role>Co-Principal Investigator</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Rubao</givenName>
          <surName>Ji</surName>
        </individualName>
        <electronicMailAddress>rji@whoi.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8839-5427</userId>
        <role>Co-Principal Investigator</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Steven</givenName>
          <surName>Lentz</surName>
        </individualName>
        <electronicMailAddress>slentz@whoi.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7498-0281</userId>
        <role>Co-Principal Investigator</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Joel</givenName>
          <surName>Llopiz</surName>
        </individualName>
        <electronicMailAddress>jllopiz@whoi.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7584-7471</userId>
        <role>Co-Principal Investigator</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Susanne</givenName>
          <surName>Menden-Deuer</surName>
        </individualName>
        <electronicMailAddress>smenden@uri.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8434-4251</userId>
        <role>Co-Principal Investigator</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Michael</givenName>
          <surName>Neubert</surName>
        </individualName>
        <electronicMailAddress>mneubert@whoi.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8820-5008</userId>
        <role>Co-Principal Investigator</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Tatiana</givenName>
          <surName>Rynearson</surName>
        </individualName>
        <electronicMailAddress>rynearson@uri.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2951-0066</userId>
        <role>Co-Principal Investigator</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Rachel</givenName>
          <surName>Stanley</surName>
        </individualName>
        <electronicMailAddress>rstanle2@wellesley.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4860-2476</userId>
        <role>Co-Principal Investigator</role>
      </personnel>
      <abstract>
        <para>The Northeast U.S. Shelf (NES) Long-Term Ecological Research (LTER) project integrates observations, experiments, and models to understand and predict how planktonic food webs are changing, and how those changes impact the productivity of higher trophic levels. The NES-LTER is co-located with the Northeast U.S. Continental Shelf Large Marine Ecosystem, spanning the Middle Atlantic Bight and Gulf of Maine. Our focal cross-shelf transect extends about 150 km southward from Martha’s Vineyard, MA, to just beyond the shelf break. Our overarching question is: How is climate change impacting the pelagic NES ecosystem and, in particular, affecting the relationship between compositional (e.g., species diversity and size structure) and aggregate (e.g., rates of primary production, and transfer of energy to important forage fish species) variability?</para>
      </abstract>
      <funding>
        <para>NSF Award OCE-1655686</para>
      </funding>
      <relatedProject>
        <title>RAPID: Collaborative Research: Autumn transition in plankton ecology during an ocean heatwave on the Northeast U.S. Shelf</title>
        <personnel>
          <individualName>
            <givenName>Heidi</givenName>
            <surName>Sosik</surName>
          </individualName>
          <electronicMailAddress>hsosik@whoi.edu</electronicMailAddress>
          <role>Principal Investigator</role>
        </personnel>
        <funding>NSF Award OCE-2102434</funding>
      </relatedProject>
    </project>
    <dataTable>
      <entityName>nes-lter-zooplankton-transect-inventory</entityName>
      <entityDescription>Zooplankton sample inventory for NES-LTER Transect cruises</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>nes-lter-zooplankton-transect-inventory.csv</objectName>
        <size unit="bytes">170740</size>
        <authentication method="MD5">4f8dc07d80bfa9d6b8e3d0ee57a204a9</authentication>
        <dataFormat>
          <textFormat>
            <numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
            <recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
            <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
            <simpleDelimited>
              <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
              <quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
            </simpleDelimited>
          </textFormat>
        </dataFormat>
      </physical>
      <attributeList>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>cruise</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Identifier for research cruise generally including abbreviation for research vessel and voyage number</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Identifier for research cruise generally including abbreviation for research vessel and voyage number</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>Missing value</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>station</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>longitudinal stations along established NES-LTER transect and MVCO; if station does not begin with an L, it is an opportunistic sample collected off of the longitudinal transect.</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>longitudinal stations along established NES-LTER transect and MVCO; if station does not begin with an L, it is an opportunistic sample collected off of the longitudinal transect.</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>Missing value</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>cast</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>CTD rosette cast number chronological per cruise</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>natural</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">1</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">45</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>Missing value</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>cast_type</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>oblique or vertical net casts</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <enumeratedDomain>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>oblique</code>
                    <definition>Single net or net pair oblique tow http://vocab.nerc.ac.uk/collection/B07/current/NDT007/</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>vertical</code>
                    <definition>Single net or net pair vertical tow http://vocab.nerc.ac.uk/collection/B07/current/NDT001/</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                </enumeratedDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>Missing value</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>net_type</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>type of net deployed</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <enumeratedDomain>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>Ring</code>
                    <definition>Gimbal-ring zooplankton sampler - Kozasa (1984) http://vocab.nerc.ac.uk/collection/L22/current/NETT0045/</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>Bongo</code>
                    <definition>Bongo net http://vocab.nerc.ac.uk/collection/L22/current/NETT0176/</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                </enumeratedDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>Missing value</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>mesh</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>size of the mesh of the net used</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <enumeratedDomain>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>150.0</code>
                    <definition>size of mesh is 150 microns</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>335.0</code>
                    <definition>size of mesh is 335 microns</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>20.0</code>
                    <definition>size of mesh is 20 microns</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                </enumeratedDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>Missing value</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>purpose</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>intention for collecting sample</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <enumeratedDomain>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>DNA</code>
                    <definition>used for meta-barcoding of entire sample</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>morphID</code>
                    <definition>used for morphological identification</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>stableisotope</code>
                    <definition>used for stable isotope analysis</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>taxapicking</code>
                    <definition>used to select single taxa for stable isotopes, DNA barcoding, morphological ID, or other opportunistic analysis</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>other</code>
                    <definition>use undecided</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                </enumeratedDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>Missing value</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>stableisotope_sizerange</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>smaller to larger range of um of sample sieves</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <enumeratedDomain>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>&gt;1000</code>
                    <definition>ambient zooplankton greater than 1000 microns</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>&gt;500&amp;&lt;1000</code>
                    <definition>ambient zooplankton greater than 500 and smaller than 1000 microns</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>&gt;200&amp;&lt;500</code>
                    <definition>ambient zooplankton greater than 200 and smaller than 500microns</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>&gt;100&amp;&lt;200</code>
                    <definition>ambient zooplankton greater than 100 and smaller than 200 microns</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>&gt;20&amp;&lt;100</code>
                    <definition>ambient zooplankton greater than 20 and smaller than 100 microns</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                </enumeratedDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>Missing value</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>PI_recipient</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>PI or lab that will be responsible for storing or processing the sample.</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <enumeratedDomain>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>Rynearson</code>
                    <definition>Tatiana Rynearson, URI</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>Llopiz</code>
                    <definition>Joel Llopiz, WHOI</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>Richardson</code>
                    <definition>David Richardson, NOAA NEFSC</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                </enumeratedDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>Missing value</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>fixative</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>method of preservation used on the sample</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <enumeratedDomain>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>EtOH</code>
                    <definition>95% Ethanol</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>Frz</code>
                    <definition>Frozen at minimum -20C</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>F/SW</code>
                    <definition>12% formalin (buffered) and filtered seawater</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                </enumeratedDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>Missing value</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>net_fraction</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>if not whole net, the portion of the net that comprises the sample</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">0.125</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">1</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>Missing value</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>no_of_jars</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>if the sample is large and was split between multiple jars, record the number of jars or vials (jars used an synonym for whatever container type the sample is preserved in)</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>whole</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">3</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>Missing value</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>comments_logsheets</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>comments from the paper fieldsheets</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>comments from the paper fieldsheets</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>Missing value</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>comments_reMissingSample</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>comments on why a sample is missing</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>comments on why a sample is missing</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>Not Applicable</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
      </attributeList>
      <numberOfRecords>976</numberOfRecords>
    </dataTable>
  </dataset>
  <additionalMetadata>
    <metadata>
      <emlEditor>
        <app>EMLassemblyline</app>
        <release>3.5.5</release>
      </emlEditor>
    </metadata>
  </additionalMetadata>
</eml:eml>
